<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An orthodox plea for the sanctuary of God, common service, white robe of the house being writ for the good of all, but more especially intended for the common sort, being composed in a stile fittest for their capacities / by G.A. Sometime of Oxford, of St. Johns.</title>
            <author>Alsop, George, b. 1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25199</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A2902</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16186</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12280201</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12280201</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58677</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25199)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58677)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 856:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An orthodox plea for the sanctuary of God, common service, white robe of the house being writ for the good of all, but more especially intended for the common sort, being composed in a stile fittest for their capacities / by G.A. Sometime of Oxford, of St. Johns.</title>
                  <author>Alsop, George, b. 1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11], 90, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and sold by R. Reynolds ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to George Alsop. cf. BM.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:58677:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait (head and shoulders) in oval frame of man in ecclesiastical robe; bottom center of oval frame contains a small coat of arms; outside the oval frame, below left and right, a bible and a Book of Common Prayer, respectively</figDesc>
                  <p>Bible</p>
                  <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prayer Book</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This but the ſhade of him adorn'd in White</l>
                     <l>Whoſe real ſubſtance doth maintaine each rite</l>
                     <l>of Gods true Church: her Comlie Decencie</l>
                     <l>in ſpite of Turke or Pope's ſupremacie</l>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58677:1"/>
            <p>An Orthodox PLEA For the
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sanctuary of God,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Common Service,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>White Robe of the Houſe,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Being writ for the good of all, but more eſpecially intended for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort; being compoſed in a Stile fitteſt for their Capacities.</p>
            <p>By <hi>G. A.</hi> Sometime of <hi>Oxford,</hi> of St. <hi>JOHNS.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm 150.1.</hi>
               </bibl> Praiſe ye God in his Sanctuary.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matthew 21.13.</hi>
               </bibl> My Houſe ſhall be called the Houſe of Prayer.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm 119.8.</hi>
               </bibl> I will keep thy Ceremonies: Oh forſake me not.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author, and ſold by <hi>R. Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds</hi> at the Sun and Bible in the Poſtern. 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:58677:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58677:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Reverend Father in God, HENERY By Divine Providence, <hi>Lord Biſhop of Chicheſter,</hi> Grace and Peace be multiplyed upon You everlaſtingly.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend in Chriſt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVEre I not aſſured that that Humility which dwels in your ſelf could conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to ſtoop, and view the ſmalleſt good with propitious eyes, I durſt not thus have tender'd this ſmall Peice unto your gracious Aſpect; but
<pb facs="tcp:58677:3"/> being confident of your great love to things though ne'r ſo low and weak, I am incouraged in this my mean addreſs to appear (before your Lordſhip) and now what Iv'e writ and offer'd here, it is your Lordſhips due, and 'twere a ſin almoſt as high as Sacriledge, to keep it back, I am obliged for ever to pay unto your ſelf much more than ordinary thanks; It was you that ſent me forth, and bid me teach: It was your hands by impoſition warranted my Call; It was your Holy Prayers that called a bleſſing down on what you did, and what I undertook; of which then I found, and ſtill do finde bleſſed effects. Now not to own ſo great a good as this, it were too evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent I had forgot how to be good; but ſure my right hand muſt forget it's Cunning, when I neglect to pay a due ſo duly juſt: I muſt confeſs my Offering is but ſmall for what I then, and ſince received, to recompence it
<pb facs="tcp:58677:3"/> were impoſible; but yet to make my poor indeavours in ſome ſence to be owned, I muſt avow and will, this poor Work of mine appears with free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from my heart, that well could wiſh it more, and better too he will indeavour, may this now be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>From him whoſe high am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition is to ſerve your Lordſhip, and the Church.</hi> G. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58677:4"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous and true Religious Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe occaſion of writing this following Treatiſe, was from the conſideration of that lamentable blindeneſs, that obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate perverſeneſs hath bred into many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Houſe of God, his Sacred Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and orderly Worſhip; and moſt eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the people of this our Nation have been led into this wickedneſs, and that which is the greateſt grief, too many of them love to continue ſo ſtill; the ponderous continuance of error hath dwelt upon them, and <hi>Iſſachar</hi>-like bend under their burthen with content; Cuſtome we ſay it is a ſecond nature, and this is too plainly ſeen amongſt many that
<pb facs="tcp:58677:4"/> ſtand in oppoſition to Gods Worſhip; they have been ſo long left to themſelves, that they have quite forgot themſelves; for when there was no King to govern <hi>Iſrael,</hi> then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one did what ſeemed good in his own eyes. Oh how eaſily were the rude multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude perſwaded by a few years continuance of diſorderly Rebellion, that blaſphemous confuſion, was the orderly government both of State and Church; ſo well pleaſed were ſome from the uſe of it that they could wiſh, and did deſire no better ſettlement, by which corruption hundreds, nay thouſands were putrified and become abominable, both to the eyes of God, and all good men, this was and is the dreadful effects of forſaking Truth to imbrace Error, they are given up to a reprobate ſence, according to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, to believe lyes that they may be damn'd; for upon Gods departing from any, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil enters them, <hi>Jus Vacui:</hi> Thus did the Devil Lord it here for ſome time, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the eſtimation and glory before God; but now to the glory of our true everlaſting God, the happineſs of our King and Church, be it
<pb facs="tcp:58677:5"/> ſpoken, this dark and helliſh Scene is blown over, and Light and Truth appears moſt gloriouſly:<note place="margin">In the Rubrick.</note> God give us hearts to be thankful, <hi>not onely with our lips, but in our lives;</hi> Whereas Murder, Blaſphemy, and Rebellion, had almoſt ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed theſe poor Kingdoms up like an unruly inundation that breaks in by force, and will do miſchief though oppoſed: So now Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Juſtice, Truth and Righteouſneſs do like pleaſant Rivers run through the midſt of them, whereas before the great Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than of Hell took his paſtime here, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered nothing to float above him that was within his reach, but made a prey thereof; ſo now with joy we may behold the Ark of God eſcapt thoſe ſtormes and dangerous threatnings, and landed ſafely on the Mountain <hi>Ararat:</hi> It is time, high time that now we ſhould appear above the Deck, and with the Prophet ſing <hi>The People that were in darkneſs have ſeen a glorious light;</hi> for know that our deliverance from the late lamentable darkneſs, was as the Children of <hi>Iſraels</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> it came
<pb facs="tcp:58677:5"/> unlookt for. Since then that God hath thus redeemed us, let's praiſe his Holy Name, and not affront his glorious love and light by willful ignorance, ſet on purpoſe to abuſe his ſacred goodneſs.</p>
            <p>It is no great ſhame to be ignorant of ſome natural things; <hi>Pariſienſis</hi> obſerves to ask a man if he can draw a Picture, penſil a Landſcip to the full; he will anſwer you without ſhame and bluſhing <hi>Neſcio,</hi> He hath no skill. But ask a man if he knows how to live holy, and worſhip God aright, that puts him to the bluſh, he is aſhamed to anſwer <hi>Neſcio;</hi> It is therefore the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Gods true Worſhip and Service that makes many not to live upright to God as they ſhould, though their pretences be never ſo ſeemingly zealous; for it is the want of being well grounded and principled in true Religion, which makes ſo many run, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, and labor after ſo many new fangled Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and prejudicial Errors as they do.</p>
            <p>It is the Houſe that is built upon the Sand that ſwims away with every Flood, whilſt the Houſe that is built upon the Rock ſtands
<pb facs="tcp:58677:6"/> it out, the Gates of Hell cannot prevail to turn it over; indeed it is almoſt impoſſible for men to live holy before God, which knows not his way of Worſhip, nor which way to go about to ſerve him.</p>
            <p>Strange fire it is abominable, it is the Sacrifice that is kindled by the ancient Coals under the Altar, which was firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed from heaven that makes the Offering pleaſant unto God: But now, good Reader, not to ſtay thee too long from what I have intended for thee, I will add but this, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe this Piece with charity as well towards the Work, as him that writ it, and know it is honeſtly intended more to do good than to get applauſe; thus candidly conceive of him, and it, and thou wilt oblige him that is thy friend to ſerve thee ſtill, whilſt thou with zeal ſhalt truly fear thy God, honour the King, and love the Church.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58677:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE</hi> Sanctuary of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD from the very beginning hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways had a Place ſet apart for his Divine Worſhip and Service to be performed in, where with Reverence and Obedience the Creatures acknowledgements were ſtill offered up to the Creators acceptance.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Adam</hi> our firſt Parent in Paradiſe had where to preſent himſelf before the Lord,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.3.</note> and <hi>Adams</hi> Sonns out of Paradiſe had where to bring their Sacrifices and Oblations unto God; the Holy Patriarchs had their Groves and Mountains for their Solemn Worſhip,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.1.</note> and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58677:7"/> when they had no ſetled Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but were as Pilgrims here on Earth, yet ſuch was Gods care to have a Church, a place to be worſhipped in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them to make a movea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Tabernacle,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.</note> that never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs for all their diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of ſettlement, they might carry their conſecrated Manſion with them where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they went: and this hath been the deſire of God in all Ages, that he might have a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Place ſet apart for his Holineſs to be worſhipped in, and that whatever Fabricks we built or erected, either Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces for the honour of Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or Schools for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Learning, Houſes for Commerce, Trade, or common uſes, that we ſhould be ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly careful as to leave room
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58677:7"/> enough for the Temple of the Lord to be built on the beſt and higheſt Ground; ſo that by a deſcent, advantage as well as right of preheminence, it might overtop the ſtatelieſt Palace, as well as the more common and inferiour Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, we here muſt own that in the infancie of the World, the Houſe and place of Gods Worſhip, was but of a ſmall ſtature, a very fit Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle for her Comers, which were but ſmall; but as Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on grew and increaſt, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſt the Houſe of God from Altars to Groves, from Altars and Groves to Mountains; from Mountains to Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; from Tabernacles, to Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues and Temples. Thus the dignity and excellency of Gods Houſe increaſt, until
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58677:8"/> it arriv'd to what luſter the Law could give it; And as in the Law ſo in the Goſpel, for in the primitive appearance of Chriſtianity, the Church and Place of Gods Worſhip was but low and mean: It firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in Woods and Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, but as the Chriſtiain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion grew and increaſt into eſteem, ſo increaſt the Houſe of God from Woods and Mountaines,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.1.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.1.</note> to Rooms and Chambers within doors; from Rooms and Chambers,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.19.</note> to Chappels,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20.</note> Churches, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrals.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple was not from the beginning, no more were ours, but arriv'd by an orderly growth to what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection they now appear at: Damnable then is their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on who would not allow of Chriſts Houſe to be one inch
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58677:8"/> bigger, nor one glimpſe light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomer than ſhe was in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive and perſecuting times of Chriſtianity. Now let but reaſon be the Judge how foul and cruel this Helliſh tenure is to be ſatisfied in nothing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the ruine of Chriſts Temples, that with thoſe wretches in the Prophet,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Haggai.</hi> 1, 4.</note> can be content to let the Houſes of of the Lord lye waſte, while their own Houſes are ſeiled and compleat: Of a certain the maintainers of this wicked opinion could willingly ſee with content of minde ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther barbarous and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Herod</hi> alive, a people as refractory as the obſtinate Jews, and all to leſſen the Lords Houſe to crucifie Chriſt over again, to ſwim and bathe themſelvs in Orthodox blood; why this muſt be, and nothing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58677:9"/> elſe could be lookt for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, ſhould the Houſe of the Lord be brought down to its primitive dejectedneſs, Chriſt muſt be murder'd in his Miniſters and Profeſſors, for there's no truer Omen of the people of Gods calamity, than when the Houſe of the Lord is held in contempt, and by Hereſie and Schiſm eclips'd. Oh how doth <hi>Jeremiah</hi> mourn for the breach that he ſaw made in the Houſe of God! The Prophet <hi>David</hi> could not ſleep neither night nor day,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.1.</note> but was in a continual diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſement of ſpirit, until he had found out a place for the Lord to be worſhipt in. <hi>Lord remember</hi> David <hi>in all his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</hi> He would not climb up to his bed, until he had found out a place for the Lord to be worſhip't in: <hi>What</hi> ſaith
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58677:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Prophet, <hi>ſhall I dwell in Cedars, and the Ark of the Lord without doors under Curtains?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis obſerv'd in this very thing, that even Pagans and Infidels are careful to build Temples and glorious Orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for the worſhip of their falſe Deities, and ſhall Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm outſtrip Chriſtianity? Shall they worſhip their Idols in Temples devoted and ſet apart for that uſe onely, and ſhall not Chriſtianity have a conſecrated Houſe ſet apart for the true God to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in? Heaven forbid Oh ſuch impiety, it is the very road to Atheiſm, for that ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damning ſin, 'tis commonly entred upon much like the pleaſing ſin of theft, it begins with a pin, and ends with a bigger thing: thus ill-princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled men, not being faſtned by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58677:10"/> grace into Gods true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, firſt begin to rob God of one ſmall Glory, then of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that's bigger, until they have robb'd him of all that they can or dare. Firſt, they begin to cavil and grumble at the number, as well as the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Churches, then at Revenues; Oh ſie, cry they, its too much by half: Next at the Ornaments, the windows they are too gawdy, this Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar that's too ſuperſtitious, the Commandments too Moſaical, the Bells they make too much noiſe, and then at the laſt they ſtrike at the whole; why not another Houſe, as well as this? Thus from one objection to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, they never leave ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting, until they have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected God quite out of doors, and his Houſe into a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteem. But this is not all, they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58677:10"/> ſtop not here; for being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven over to a reprobate ſenſe, as the Apoſtle well notes, the Devil is ſtill animating them on to further miſchief, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial of goodneſs, for from a diſeſteem of Gods Houſe, they come to a diſeſteem of the pure and ſacred Word of God, which is able to make the whole World wiſe unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; they then pretend they have no need of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ti's but a dead Letter, cries ſome wretches, they have a quickening ſpirit within them that informs them all things, there's too too many of theſe that from a denial of Gods Houſe comes to a denial of his Word, and from that they arrive at laſt without Gods reſtraining grace to that woful pitch of reprobation and eternal damnation, even
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58677:11"/> to the denying of the Lord that bought them; and this was too plainly ſeen in our late blaſphemous and rebell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous times, when almoſt every apoſtatizing Sect dare take the Wall of Gods pure Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, turning Religion into the Channel; Nay ſome there were that imp't themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that pitch of impiety and and ſtrange audacious bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>James Naylor</hi> the Quaker entring the Ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Briſtol</hi> on an Aſs.</note> that <hi>Phaeton</hi>-like preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to take upon them the reines of government as the Son of God, aſſumed his name, entred the City with ſhouts and acclamations of <hi>Hoſanna.</hi> Now what more horrid blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy could be acted than this in the face of God, Angels and men?</p>
               <p>It is dangerous my friends to fall out of Gods protection into Satans ruine, to forſake
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58677:11"/> the Living Water, and to dig unto your ſelves Ciſterns that will hold no Water.</p>
               <p>It is obſerved that naturally Religion and ſerving of God,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Brownrig</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
                  </note> conſults with the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> If there be a God and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then there muſt be a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and if a Worſhip, then a Tabernacle or Temple; and if ſo, then it muſt be anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his glory in a comely manner. Let us but conſider the amiable beauty and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendent glory of that Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which <hi>Solomon</hi> built for God, the great care, coſt, pains and induſtry in the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it, that all things in ſome meaſure might be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable for the entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo great a God that was to dwell in it. The Gold was fetcht from <hi>Ophir,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 5. <hi>Ch.</hi>
                  </note> the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar Trees from <hi>Lebanon,</hi> the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58677:12"/> Braſs from <hi>Corinth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joſephus.</note> the Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Workmen from <hi>Tyrus,</hi> and all to erect up a Fabrick for Gods Worſhip; and now to all this zealous induſtry of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.12, 13.</note> ſee what an incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment God adds to it concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this Houſe which thou haſt built, <hi>If thou walkeſt in my Ordinances—I will dwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Children of Iſrael, and will not forſake my people Iſrael.</hi> And accordingly as God did promiſe, ſo he performed; for when the Houſe was finiſhed and made perfect, God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends in a Cloud and takes poſſeſſion of it;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.10.</note> and this God did for two purpoſes; Firſt to keep the Founders off for lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Title, Claim, or After-intereſt to that which he had re-entred upon, and made his own by lawful poſſeſſion. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to imprint a reverent
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58677:12"/> acknowledgment of the houſe from all men, that that place muſt needs be holy where God dwels and inhabits.</p>
               <p>But here I know ſome will be ready to ſtep in and ſay, <hi>Why? 'Tis known that all this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and coſt which was beſtowed, on</hi> Solomons <hi>Temple, it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the time of the Law, which we have nothing to do withal.</hi> Now how eaſily may this be anſwered? Is not God the God of the Law as well as the Goſpel, and of the Goſpel as well as the Law? Is he not <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Ending? Is he not to be worſhipped now as well as then? Hath he not a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for ever? And though our Saviours coming aboliſht the Jewiſh Ceremonies, the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the Law by offering up himſelf once for all; and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58677:13"/> though <hi>Moſes</hi> gave place and reſignation of precedency to Chriſt, all this and what ever he did, it aim'd not at the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of the Temple, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting it to any baſe and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior uſe: No our bleſſed Savior is ſo far from pulling down this glorious Temple built to his Fathers ſervice, or to allow of any imployment that it ſhould be put to beyond what it was fitſt intended for, that he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to correct the Jews unhallowing of the ſame, and to let them roundly know that it was not fit ſuch a holy place dedicated to his Fathers uſe, ſhould be made a place of Mart and Trade, It's worth our obſervation, and it doth much conduce to the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es benefit, if conſidered, the ardent vehemency of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viors zeal; at this time onely,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58677:13"/> and at all other times, calm, the Jews ſpit upon him, buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetted him, and ſcorned him, crown'd his head with thorns, nailed him to the Croſs, yet all this and more ſtirs him not, he paſſes it away in ſilence: But oh the abuſe of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe, that moves him to a heavenly anger, I and the ſequal plainly confirms it; for he never ſtands much to pauſe and argue with them for their unreverent carriages and performances in the Houſe of his Father, but gets him a Whip of Cords and to work with them ſoundly;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.</note> He overturns the Table of the Money-Changers, and leaves them ſcrambling for their Coin, and makes the Dove-Sellers take up their heels and flie for it, and in the general tells them all, <hi>It is written,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.13.</note> 
                  <hi>My
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58677:14"/> Houſe ſhall be called a Houſe of Prayer, but ye have made it a den of thieves.</hi> Bleſt be this holy preſident that our Savior hath taught and left us, by it we ſee we ought not, nor muſt not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the houſe of the Lord to be uſed irreverently, or to be abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or turn'd to contrary ends from what it was intended. And we finde to back this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident the good Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> following the example of his Maſter Jeſus, he ſeverely corrects the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for their unſeemly behaviour to the Houſe of God. Now theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> it is ſuppoſed had had the Houſe of God ſo long in their own houſes, by reaſon of perſecution, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to eſteem it no better than their ordinary dwelling where they eat and drank, feaſted and revelled: but mark how
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58677:14"/> ſharply St. <hi>Paul</hi> takes them up for it.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.22.</note> 
                  <hi>What have ye not hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to eat and drink in; but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe ye the Houſe of God?</hi> Here St. <hi>Paul</hi> argues the difference between a common houſe and the Houſe of God,<note place="margin">Being the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Church.</note> I and thus God himſelf of old commands a reverence to his Houſe, for when God gave the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to the Children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> that they ſhould keep his Sabbath, ſee what he linkes to it, <hi>you ſhall keep my Sabbath,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and reverence my Sanctuary;</hi> as if the Sabbath could not be kept in a right holy obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, without a reverent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Houſe of God.</p>
               <p>But here I know ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will be apt to ſay, <hi>They could like it may be the place that is appointed for Worſhip, were it not for this, the Founders and Builders of them were Idolaters,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58677:15"/> they worſhipped falſe gods, as Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and the like, and therefore ſay they, we hold them not fit for the true God to be worſhipped, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were firſt ſet apart and devoted to falſe gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That we are not to forſake the Houſe of God, now in being, becauſe Idolaters firſt founded and built the Houſe before it was the Houſe of God, for know that it was not the firſt found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or builders of the Houſes or Churches, made them the Houſes of God, but the holy and reverend Dedication and Conſecration of them ſince, and were not this allowable, undoubtedly our Forefathers would not have received the Temples of Idols,<note place="margin">Pet. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. Com. Pla.</note> and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them into holy Houſes where Chriſt ſhould be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, and thoſe Revenues
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58677:15"/> that were dedicated to their Gods and Goddeſſes, to Plays and Veſtal Virgins, to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing of Churches, and maintenance of Miniſters, whereas theſe things did not onely at firſt ſerve Anti-Chriſt but even the Devil himſelf; you might as well deny almoſt every thing that you neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily and commonly uſe, as this. For know if you will uſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that hath been dedicated to Paganiſm or Idolatry, you muſt drink no wine; for the Heathens conſecrated it to <hi>Bachus;</hi> nor eat no bread, for they conſecrated it to <hi>Ceres;</hi> Water to <hi>Neptune,</hi> Learning to <hi>Mercury,</hi> but this obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance were ridiculous; for as learned Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> ſpeaks in his <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Polity,</hi> Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters may judge even what is decent about external affairs
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58677:16"/> of God, as of greater thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that are true, yet nevertheleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what ever Idolaters hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thought or done idolatrouſly let it be abhor'd, yet of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which is good even in evi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things God is the Author; Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould we forſake thoſe part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that are good in Idolaters, we might forſake many things and thoſe ſubſtantial too without which there would be no ſalvation; we might then ceaſe to believe in God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, with other neceſſary points, all which Papiſtical Idolaters believe, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. But in this we ought to be very careful that we do not preſs and burthen the people of God with any ſuch bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, as to let them uſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that Idolaters hath uſed, being lawful before God. I
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58677:16"/> ask the Queſtion whether the people of God did diſown the Ark becauſe the Philiſtines played and ſported with it? It was not their carrying of it from <hi>Gath</hi> to <hi>Ekron,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Askelon,</hi> no they received it with joy, when once God returned it to them again? Were the people of God to diſeſteem the Houſe of the Lord, becauſe <hi>Manaſſes</hi> was an Idolatrous King, and built up Altars in the Houſe of the Lord unto falſe gods,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.</note> and worſhipped them when he had done? No upon the Lords chaſtiſing of him, and his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to the true Religion, pulling down thoſe Altars that were built up to falſe gods, and erecting an Altar to the true God, the ſame Houſe continu'd ſerviceable ſtill; thus the conſecrated Cenſers that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58677:17"/> 
                  <hi>Corah</hi> and his Complices uſed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.37.38.</note> were not to be thrown away, though they imployed them to a moſt prophane uſe, no more are our Churches to be refrained, becauſe they have been Idolatrouſly abuſed (as I have noted before) for if we muſt pull down our Churches for former polutions, then have we work enough to do, not onely in reſpect of the Papiſts abuſe at firſt, but in reſpect alſo of the late abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable corruptions, that the laſt wicked times ſtained them withal; for it is not unknown to many, that ſome of our Churches which were conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to Gods ſervice were then converted to baſe and abominable uſes, very few to any good; for thoſe that they did not make Stables, and Ware houſes, they made them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58677:17"/> the Conventicles of Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Nonſence, and Rebellion; for in them they have with more than ordinary confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence prayed as they called it, to the God of mercy, that he would aſſiſt them in the work of revenge, and deſtruction againſt King, Prieſt, and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; in them they animated the Father againſt the Son, and the Son againſt the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;<note place="margin">See at large Reverend Dr. <hi>King,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ciciſter,</hi> in a Sermon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> preacht be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty the 30 <hi>Jan.</hi>
                  </note> in them they maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it was no ſin to murder Gods anointed, to baniſh and illegally ſuſpend his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; ſure then the Houſes of God were ſufficiently abuſed; Here the Church had cauſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to cry out, <hi>Was ever ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row like mine?</hi> Yet all this, and more injuries offered to her, though they were great griefs in their time, yet not cauſe enough to make the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58677:18"/> People of the Lord to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteem or forget her, but with <hi>Iſraels</hi> Captives they ſtill did ſing, <hi>If I forget thee, Oh Houſe of God, let my right hand forget its cunning.</hi> It is not any thing indeed that can be uſ'd againſt Gods Houſe that can make the Orthodox-chriſtian diſ-eſteem it; No, he mourns with her in adverſity, and rejoyceth with her in proſperity, never forgetting her howe're ſhe is dealt with: There are too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I would I could not ſpeak it, that now appears in the vindication of the Houſe of God, becauſe they ſee ſhe's highly favoured of the Lord; that ſhould ſhe ever be eclips't again, which I heartily pray may never be, would ſoon draw from her, and prove the very worſt of enemies. There is too too many of theſe falſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58677:18"/> hearted Sycophants, that can cry all hail to day and cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie to morrow, that ſerve her more for profit than they do for love. Oh that the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhops and my very good Superiours, with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion be it ſpoken, would think on ſome way to purge our Church from baſe tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing Pulpitters, ſuch that whindle, cry, bemoan and fawn upon her in publike, that too frequently ſtab her to the heart in private; that wait and pray for another wicked change; that they might be uppermoſt again, but from ſuch falſe hearted <hi>Proteus's</hi> that turns to every ſide, that can be a prick-ear'd Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick to day, and a ſeeming Orthodox-Chriſtian to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, that can off with a Jump, and on with a Caſſock,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58677:19"/> that can ſwallow a large Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Covenant, without ſtrein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at it, from all ſuch in the words of the Letany, <hi rend="blackletterType">Good Lord deliver us.</hi> But oh the true Orthodox-Servant of God, which ſtands unwavering to his original principle, that doth not ſay with him that went to Maſs,<note place="margin">To tullian.</note> 
                  <hi>Eamus ad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munem errorem,</hi> Lets yield to common errour. 'Tis not the torrent of common practice can draw the religious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian from his true grounded reſolution: 'twas not the prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of a Living of a hundred a year, or Chaplain to <hi>Nol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> could do it; they were like <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nego,</hi> they'l die firſt; they are no ſtarters, nor flinchers, but like <hi>Davids</hi> Worthies ſtick to her in all her troubles; Sons of the Church, and not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58677:19"/> the Kirk; they are builders and not deſtroyers of the Houſe of God; that repair her breaches, and not rend them wider; that reverence the Houſe as the Habitation of God, and not ſcornfully ſet by it as a place of no worth or value: of a certain I may ſpeak it, and that within com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, that there are none but a ſort of mad and perverſe Rake-hels that ſin againſt the light of Reaſon and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that will not allow God the ſame benefit they have themſelves to dwell in a houſe; but let ſuch invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and erroneous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments aim as deſtructively as ever they can againſt the Dwelling of the Lord, God hath, and ſhall for ever have a Houſe for his Honor to dwell in.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:58677:20"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">For while there is a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church upheld by God, ſo long will there be a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial houſe for his people to worſhip in, kept up by the ſame power; for 'tis not the devil nor mans envy, can harm either viſible or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial, but Gods judgement for the ſin and abuſe of both is the cauſe of their deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and demoliſhing.</note>A Houſe built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Rock, the gates of hell ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt it, and of a certain that Houſe muſt needs be ſtrong then where Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency is the Head of the Building, and a continual Providence to ſupport it; Read but the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient prophecy of Gods houſe the ſtability, honor, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Though theſe Scriptures are by moſt taken by Gods viſible Church, and not for the material Church made of wood, iron, and ſtones, yet if we conſider that the viſible Church of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cannot wel worſhip God without a place ſet apart to worſhip him in, we may in ſome ſort eſtabliſh a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity to theſe our material buildings which we cal Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and think them, at leaſt ſome of them, to be built on a Rock, againſt which mens malice ſhall not prevail.</note>
                  <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in the laſt days, that the Mountains of the Lords Houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the top of the Mountain, and ſhall be exalted above the Hills, and all Nations ſhall flow unto it, and many people ſhall go, and ſay,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58677:20"/> Come ye, and let us go up to the Mountain of the Lord, to the Houſe of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and he will teach us of his ways, and we will walk in his pathes,</hi> Iſa. 2.2, 3.</p>
               <p>See here the Eminency of Gods Houſe, the Height and Glory of it! This is Gods Hill on which he dwells; For the Hill of the Lord is like the great Mountain of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> there's no removing of it: Oh how malicious then are thoſe who would level the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of God if they could, and bring in competition with the loweſt Valley? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly theſe are wretches ſtamped after the Devils own heart, not qualified like <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> after Gods own heart; who as it were dotes and falls inamored with the Houſe of God</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:58677:21"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.8.</note>
                  <hi>Oh how I have loved the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of thy Houſe, and the place where thine Honor dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.7.</note> And again, <hi>I'le come into thy Houſe in the multitude of thy Mercy, and in thy fear will I worſhip toward thy Holy Temple.</hi> Thus Holy and Religious men makes Gods Houſe a place of Fear and Reverence, they do not diſ-eſteem it, or ruſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it hand over head, making no difference between the Houſe of the Lord and the Market; of a truth they are acquainted with better things, they follow <hi>Solomons</hi> dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Take heed to thy foot when thou entreſt into the Houſe of God;</hi> they are wary in all their carriages whilſt they are there, demeaning themſelves according to the ſanctity of the Place, they'l not in any action willfully tread awry,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58677:21"/> they know it is Gods Houſe, and accordingly muſt behave themſelves in it: but now the contrary, is too much the ſin of our times and unreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Houſe of God; we concieve meanly of the Houſe it ſelf, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we demean our ſelves both in it and towards it: Few in our age ſay with <hi>Jacob</hi> after his dream,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.7.</note> 
                  <hi>How fearful is this Place, this is none but the Houſe of God!</hi> But indeed it cannot well be expected that thoſe that have no reſpect towards Gods Commands, that they ſhould have any towards his Houſe; for it is a plain infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible mark or ſign, that thoſe that have no eſteem to God and true Religion, they can have no eſteem towards his Dwelling: there are many, and a very great many of them
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58677:22"/> too, that can be content to give God ſome ſlight and cheap obſervance, but if there be required from them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than ordinary to be given for the Honor and Dignity of God, either to build Churches, or to repair thoſe that are built; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the maintenance of their Miniſter, if he have not a ſufficient competency of his own, in theſe or ſuch like caſes, moſt men are apt to draw back, accounting that God and Religion beſt that's beſt cheap, thus when Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love ſways us,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Brownrig</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
                  </note> we are all for our ſelves; but true love ſeeks not his own ſo much as the glory of God. 'Tis worth our, obſervation to conſider <hi>Peters</hi> care in offering to build the Tabernacle upon Mount <hi>Tabor, Maſter, it's good for us to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58677:22"/> be here;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 9.33.</note> 
                  <hi>Let's build three Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, one for thee, one for</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>and one for</hi> Elias, mark how careful he is to build Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles for theſe three, but takes no care for himſelf, he offers to provide for them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt winde and weather, and takes no notice of his own ſhelter; and from this we may obſerve, that true love to God and his Church tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports a Chriſtian out of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, making him to forget his own comfort in reſpect of God, to take care for building Gods Tabernacle before his own. <hi>Tertullian</hi> obſerves not any that followed Chriſt that ever queſtioned how they ſhould live, None ſaid, <hi>Non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo, quo vivam, Pietas non reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit vitam, multo minus victum.</hi> Its enough for them to be in <hi>famulatu Chriſti:</hi> attendance
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58677:23"/> upon God ſhould be always or at leaſt our firſt buſineſs, we ſhould always give God the precedency of being ſerved; firſt his Houſe being firſt built or repaired,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.16.</note> and made ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable before our own; His abſolute dues firſt tendred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we reckon any thing to be our own,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.14.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.23.</note> we muſt have a care of playing falſe play with God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mallaki.</hi> 1.13.</note> tendring any thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that is unperfect, or detaining any thing from him that is his due. <hi>Abel</hi> makes choice of the beſt of his Flock, but <hi>Kain</hi> takes no ſuch care, that which comes next to hand will ſerve Gods turn well enough, he thinks; but our God abominates all ſuch uſage: he muſt have the beſt or none,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.12.</note> 
                  <hi>The beſt of the Oyl, the beſt of Wine, and the beſt of the Wheat, ſhalt thou offer unto the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58677:23"/> Lord:</hi> God accounts it fraud and couſenage to have the courſeſt Grain, the leaſt Heap, the lighteſt Sheaf. The Jews have a Witty ſaying amongſt them, That <hi>Kain was a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man, and his ſacrifice ſmelt of it;</hi> and truly the ſame ſaying may be verified in many in theſe our dayes that what they offer to God and his Houſe, it ſmells of covetouſneſs, they will as ſoon part with their lives as with any thing with a free heart towards God, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Church, and the maintenance of his Miniſtry. Hence it is that the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Laws are ſo great an eye-ſore and trouble to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, becauſe with <hi>Joſhuah</hi> they commands the People to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, to repair his Houſe, to maintain his Miniſters,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58677:24"/> to live orderly and ſoberly in all godlineſs of life; and for this reaſon do moſt hate the Laws and Inſtitutions of God, becauſe they ſtand in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all Prophaneneſs, wilful Liberty, Sacriledge, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:58677:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE</hi> Common Service.</head>
               <p>PUlbick Prayer before God it's an utterance of good and wholſome words in an orderly form ſo exactly couch't, and fore-thought on, as may be fit in an humble manner to be offered up unto the God of Order; therefore when we prepare for the Houſe of God we muſt alſo prepare in a fitted readineſs, what we ſhall have to ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, when we come before him; If for pardon of ſin and begging of ſupplies, if for giving of thanks for bleſſings and mercies received, delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances obtained, why all this
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58677:25"/> and whatever we ſhall, or may have need of to put up to God, muſt be ſeriouſly and devout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forethought of, to which intent there hath been, and is at this very day fitted for our occaſional wants, holy and profitable Supplies, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine-Service of the Church planted for a ſtable Worſhip, and Service to God for ever; So that none might ruſh into his ſacred preſence, and there pour out before the God of Order and Holineſs, a long and tedious oration, the moſt None-ſence,<note place="margin">Theſe were the common effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> Saints,</note> Blaſphemy, and Rebellion, with hum's and haw's, coughs and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent fetches. Now God of old, to prevent this ſtrange and irregular boldneſs, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed a Set-form of Worſhip that men might not take up that boldneſs to ſpeak any
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58677:25"/> thing before him raſhly, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Guiders and Paſtors of his People, And the Lord ſpake unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaying, Speak unto <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons. Thus ſhall they bleſs the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>The Lord bleſs thee and keep thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.24 25, 26.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>The Lord make his face ſhine upon thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">God himſelf did frame to his Prieſts the very ſpeech wherewith they were charged to bleſs his people.</note> 
                  <hi>and be merciful unto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Lord lift up his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance upon thee, and give thee peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not leaving the bleſſing to their own extemporary effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, 'tis plain enough known, and that beyond the reach of contradiction; that the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient People of God, the Jews had a particular Liturgy, a Form of Divine-Service ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted out of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as a conſtant Service for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58677:26"/> their approach to God upon all occaſions, their Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions being pen'd by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of their Synagogues;<note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctic. Catech.</note> Now this their Form of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as it was ordained for an exact Service to God, ſo was it alſo intended to prevent the true Religion from all corruption in Doctrine, that God might be ſerved in all places with one and the ſame Order and Form of Divine Worſhip; And as the Jews had their Forms of Divine Service, ſo had, and have the Chriſtians alſo:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 11.1.</note> 
                  <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> taught his Diſciples to pray by Form, and our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour himſelf left us a Form of Prayer, to ſignifie his allowance of that way of Worſhip, and to prevent all temeritious effuſions, as alſo to take off all quarrels that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58677:26"/> might ariſe by the ſpirits of contradictions: Our Saviour doth as it were ſtand up, and ſpeak to his Diſciples, to whom he was to leave the government of his Church af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Aſcenſion, my friends, to take away all diſputes that may be amongſt you, what kinde of worſhip my Church ſhall be ſerved withal, when ye pray ſay, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 11.2.</note> And as the Chriſtians had their Set-forms of Prayer, ſo had they alſo their Pſalms and Hymns,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26.</note> and all to make up a compleat Liturgy;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.3.</note> For when they had ſung a Pſalm they went up into the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; and as the Jews had their Songs of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1.46.</note> ſo have the Chriſtians the Songs of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1.68.</note> 
                  <hi>Zacharias</hi> and <hi>Old-Simeon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 2.29.</note> And theſe are thoſe which the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58677:27"/> Apoſtles doth ſo often ſay,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>I will pray and ſing with the Spirit.</hi> And again,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.19.</note> in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs, making melody to the Lord with my whole heart. Now we know that Hymns and Pſalms, and ſuch kinde of Prayer and Praiſes are not to be canviſed on the ſudden, but to be premeditated and framed aforehand. I, but will ſome ſay, all that St. <hi>Paul</hi> performed in this kinde, he did it by the Spirit, he prayed and ſung by the Spirit. All this we own, God forbid elſe; for know he that ventures up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Form of Prayer, or Hymn, Pſalm, or Benediction, without a devout and holy Spirit prepared for the work, doth rather prattle than pray; howl than ſing Pſalms. All Gods Prayers muſt be prayed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58677:27"/> with the Spirit, or elſe they fall under the ſcandal with thoſe that the Apoſtle ſo long ago corrects, <hi>That they uſe a Form of Godlineſs, but deny the power thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They therefore do very ill and uncharitable to the ſacred Prayers of Gods Church, to ſtigmatize it with that infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, crying of it down, that it is barely carried on by Form without any power, as if all Service and Devotion dwelt onely upon external perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances; but they that ſpeak it without book, they know not what they ſay; for indeed how dare any take up that boldneſs to themſelves to judge the heart of man, when none knows it but God. If our Worſhip be onely formal and hypocritical, as many ſay it is, I ask the Queſtion how
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58677:28"/> they know it? Our words in our Service are Gods words, our geſtures and carriages with our habits, are decent and comely, when we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our Worſhip: Now what is within us, none but God knows; for let the worſt of our enemies ſtand and behold our Order, they muſt if they will ſpeak truth,<note place="margin">When our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical voyces &amp; devout hearts according to the old Latine verſe; <hi>Non von ſed votum non chordula muſica ſed cor. Non clamor, ſed amor can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat in aure Dei.</hi>
                  </note> ſay that ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this is the place where God dwells; I muſt confeſs we cannot free our Church alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether from ſinful Paſtors, as well as refractory people; for there hath always been <hi>Mixtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Eccleſiae</hi> from the beginning, and will ſo continue: <hi>Kain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> are the Churches Repreſentatives, who ſhows a mixt temper and compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church from the beginning; ſubſtantial and falſe-hearted attenders on the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58677:28"/> Altar of God;<note place="margin">Aug Ep. <hi>145.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ad huc arca con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet corvum &amp; columbam.</hi> Clean and unclean birds; the Dove, and the Raven are both in the Ark and Houſe of God. And this hath been of old, and will continue until the great Shepheard ſhall come and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate the good from the bad, till then they feed together in the ſame paſture: But howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver though there be, and muſt be a mixture of good and bad Miniſters and People, yet the pure Worſhip and Service it ſelf is unſpotted. Prayer and Praiſes have no errours, <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum eſt errare,</hi> but Gods Service hath none; And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over in reference to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going relation, it hath been, and is always the induſtrious care of the Fathers of the Church, that none ſhould be admitted to holy Orders to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58677:29"/> attend upon Gods Altar, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out they did ſeem and appear to be as well grounded in Grace as Learning, that their offerings that they ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up to God in his holy San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, might be ſpiritual and not carnal; for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more hateful to God than a Formal Devotion without the Spirit, therefore when we pray in the Liturgy we pray earneſtly for the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the ſpirit of God. <hi rend="blackletterType">Wherefore let us beſéech him to grant us true repentance, and his holy ſpirit, that thoſe things may pleaſe him which we do at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See in the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</note> And when the Miniſter bleſſeth the people in the Lords name; <hi rend="blackletterType">The Lord be with you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See after the Creed.</note> Hee's anſwered by the whole Congregation by way of retaliation, <hi rend="blackletterType">and with thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> And again in the Litany
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58677:29"/> we pray,<note place="margin">See the Leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</note> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">That it may pleaſe God to giue us true repentance, to forgive us all our ſins, negligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; ignorances, and to endue us with the grace of his holy Spirit to amend our lives according to his holy Word.</hi> And ſo in many other of our ſeveral Collects and Prayers, we beſeech God that he would ſend down his Spirit upon us to guide and direct us. How wicked then are thoſe men that abuſe this holy Worſhip, calling it a Form without a Spirit? &amp; have given out in their preaching &amp; writings that we deny the ſpirit to have any exerciſe in our Worſhip, when God he knows it is our earneſt beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and intreating of him continually, when we appear before him in Prayer, that he would ever aſſiſt us with his holy Spirit: They therefore that do not take the Worſhip
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58677:30"/> and Service of our Church to be Spiritual and Divine, are led and conducted by no other ſpirit but the ſpirit of Errour and Contradiction. For know the Service of our Church performed cordially and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, it is a pure holy and acceptable Service, it is as pleaſing Incenſe in the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils of God, when it is fired by the ardency of Faith and true Devotion; when the Churches Worſhip is joyntly and univerſally performed throughout her ſeveral Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, obſerving and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying one and the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, though but a Church mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant, yet ſhe fairly by imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion repreſents the Church triumphant, which praiſes God in a joynt Communion, they all ſing with one and the ſame Form; <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58677:30"/> God of Sabaoth,</hi> whereas a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly Devotion in the Church, muſt ſurely as much affront God as amaze the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when the whole time at Service ſhall be ſpent in throwing out corrupt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeſted words as they happen to come uppermoſt, ſome right, ſome wrong, the Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſpending their time in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but in liſtening and conſidering what their extemporary Preacher, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pratler, with his long fetches and turns will drive at; at laſt being often out, but ſeldome in, it is therefore no wonder at all that many times the people complain that their Guides are dark and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious in their directions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo often loſt and at a ſtand themſelves in the very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing of their Rules:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58677:31"/> whereas our Service and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip it is even a guide to the ſimpleſt and loweſt of men; for certainly he muſt be of a very ſhallow capacity that cannot joyn with the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in our Prayers and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices; And undoubtedly thoſe Prayers doeth moſt good that are performed knowingly: Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in the Worſhip of God is the mother and bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der up of Error.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.29.</note> 
                  <hi>You erre,</hi> ſaith Chriſt to the Sadduces, <hi>not knowing the Word.</hi> He that prayes ignorantly, reaps lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle profit by it, whilſt he that prayes underſtandingly, reaps wiſdom unto Salvation. Oh what a goodly and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a ſight it is to ſee both Paſtor and People praying in a joynt agreement and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; for of a certain thoſe Prayers and Praiſes are likely to do moſt good that are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58677:31"/> underſtandingly, as well as publikely: for as Doct. <hi>Hamond</hi> obſerves in his <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Catechiſm,</hi> that the Union of many hearts being met together are likelieſt to prevail, and the preſence of ſome godly may bring down mercies upon others whoſe Prayers hath no promiſe to be heard, eſpecially performed by a conſecrated perſon, whoſe office is to draw nigh unto God, to offer up Prayer and Thanks-giving, as an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour between God and Man. Oh 'tis a glorious ſight to behold theſe ſacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances to be done with zeal and devotion; Certainly, as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaith, it is the Gate of Heaven. Holy-Prayer is that which pleaſeth God, &amp; advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageth Man; And if Prayer, then ſeemly and orderly Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58677:32"/> and what more orderly and ſeemly than the Holy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice that is now, bleſſed be the Lord, amongſt us; the worſt of our enemies cannot ſay it is a myſtical or intricate Worſhip delivered in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Tongue, or imbroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with canting tearms, ſuch as many of our adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Prayers are more befitting a Prologue of a Comedy, to create laughter than ſtir up zeal; the worſt they ſay of our Prayers, they are plain and homely, but theſe are unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian-like Reproches; as if any thing that acquaints the ſoul with God, or conducts it to Heaven, can be too plain and obvious; but if plain, as they ſay, let them know it is the plain Word of God, that Word which is able to make us wiſe unto Salvation; For
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58677:32"/> know that our Prayers, Pſalms, and Benedictions, are the moſt of them extracted out of the Word of God, and are me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodically placed in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly advantage for the glory of Gods Praiſe, and the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed benefit of his people that draw nigh unto him. Sure then thoſe orderly and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated Prayers and Praiſes taken out of the Word of God, may I hope as well for their antiquity as their worth, plead the preheminence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the effuſion of long and tedious extemporary Prayers, made by the vain and bold imaginations of ſome Squan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-headed fellow.</p>
               <p>But here I ſuppoſe ſome may be apt to ſtep in and ſay, <hi>Were your Service made up onely with Prayer and Praiſes, we might it may be ſooner agree and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58677:33"/> aſſent to them, but they are mixt with Prayers, and Hymns, and Pſalms, and Chapters made up altogether, it appears not at all ſo advantagious and profitable as if made up with Prayers and Praiſes onely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer; our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt left the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church upon his aſcending up on high, unto the Apoſtles, and their lawful Succeſſors, commiſſionating and binding them as <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Timothy</hi> at <hi>Creet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5.</note> to ſettle and eſtabliſh all things in an orderly advantage, as well for the praiſe of his glory as the good of his people; now whereas it is commonly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected that the mixture and variety that is in our Service makes it not approved of, nor followed by many, I thus vindicate this point in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58677:33"/> to their erroneous mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake; for know that the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of our Church would not be ſo profitable, nor ſo like to a true Worſhip that muſt be offered up to God, were it not for the change and ſucceſſion that's in it. Thus I make it appear to all reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable men, <hi>viz.</hi> When we approach to the publike Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Lord, we come or at leaſt ought ſo to do, to make our confeſſion of what ſins we have committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, 'tis but fit, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the foulneſs of our offences, to proſtrate our ſelves upon our knees before the throne of his grace, and there acknowledg with tears the pollution of our ſouls, ſaying, <hi rend="blackletterType">we have erred and ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from thy wayes, &amp;c.</hi> upon which articular acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58677:34"/> the Miniſter for comfort and conſolation doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Gods proneneſs to forgive and have mercy upon Submiſſion, which being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and the ſoul eaſed by Prayer, then to riſe with a reverend poſture from the Knees with Praiſes, <hi rend="blackletterType">O come let us ſing unto the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. upon the ending of thoſe Praiſes then to place your ſelf decent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as in the Houſe of God, waiting and receiving with an open Soul thoſe holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions from Gods Word that ſhall be read unto you, and firſt the Pſalms of <hi>David, Gloria Patri</hi> being ended, then a Leſſon out of the old Teſtament moſt commonly relating to the antient promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and kindneſſes of God to his Church, in conſideration 'tis but meet to give him
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58677:34"/> praiſe, ſinging or ſaying that ſacred Hymn, <hi>Te Deum Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus.</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">We Praiſe thée O God,</hi> &amp;c. then after a Leſſon out of the New Teſtament declaring the performance of his promiſed mercy to his Church, to ſing another Hymn, <hi rend="blackletterType">Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael,</hi> &amp;c. then ſtoutly to ſtand with a direct body, as well as an even ſoul, like a true heroick Soldier of God, and make a confeſſion of thy Faith, ſpeaking with an audible voice, <hi rend="blackletterType">I believe in God,</hi> &amp;c. then to bow your ſelf in Prayer before God, for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers neceſſities of humane Nature,<note place="margin">The Lords Prayer and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with the Letany.</note> not onely for your ſelf but for others, the King, and the whole Kingdom, yea even for the converting of your enemies; then after a ſpecial prayer for Grace and Sanctification, the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58677:35"/> with the Epiſtles and Goſpels being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinctly deliverd unto us, the one containing our duty both to God and man, the other having aſpeciall relation to the work of our redemption;<note place="margin">See a <hi>Peice</hi> Printed at <hi>Cambridge</hi> 1642 called the Proteſtant Account.</note> all and what ever remains of the ſervice of the Church elſe being in order and due man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner plac't for the Glory of Gods Worſhip, and the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient advantage of his Peoples Souls, muſt needs be approved of from God, and all good and Religious men.</p>
               <p>But I know ſome others wil be apt to ſay for all this, <hi>That though the words may be good and the Order plauſible, yet the length and tediouſneſs of them keeps them longer out of the Church than they would be: Oh ſay ſome, they ſtop us an unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able while from hearing of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58677:35"/> Sermon, and were it not for this fault, we would hear them oftner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why theſe are ſtrange ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and too often uſ'd in this ſinful Nation, that Prayer and Praiſes unto God ſhould be counted tedious and irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, this is quite contrary to the Apoſtles ſaying, <hi>Pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.</hi> Now whereas 'tis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected that the Prayers of the Church keeps people from the Sermon too long, 'tis a folly beyond wonder to conſider it that ever people ſhould be ſo ignorant of the excellency of Divine Prayer and Praiſes, which are the golden Keys that open and ſhut the gates of Heaven; that wreſtle with God, and command his mercy down, as it were, that this Sacred Worſhip ſhould be joſtled out of the Church, or at leaſt ſo little ſet by, that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58677:36"/> Preaching a thing that hath been more commoner in our age, to ſavour of wit and humour than any true devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhould be prefer'd before it. I muſt confeſs I have been always,<note place="margin">God forbid I ſhould deny the Ordinance of ſound Preaching but the abuſe of it I abhor from my heart, when Sermons leds people to Heaven, Oh then they are good, but when they direct for Hell, when murder and Rebellion is the Theame of the Pulpit, and confuſed Extravagancy the whole matter that's raiſed from it, then to hate ſuch Preaching is commendable: why this was the preaching of the late times, and too many <hi>I</hi> am afraid uſe it ſtill, this was the vomits of the Pulpit when that wretch <hi>Peters</hi> aſſum'd the Chair of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
                  </note> and am ſtill a Lover of true Preaching, but not at all of that which many call, and would have paſs for preaching, to name a text and then to talk any thing that comes uppermoſt from it; either to run ſo far from the text as never to come near it after once nam'd, or to crow'd ſo cloſe to it as to ſcrew it beyond its height, making the true word of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58677:36"/> God to ſpeak that which it never intended, certainly ſuch preaching as this muſt much abuſe the word of God, the Hearers, and their owne ſouls that vent it, when as a neat, quaint and zealous expoſition upon the words is commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with allowance, to Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe with ſincerity &amp; trueth, neither wreſting the word from its intended ſcope, or drift, nor aſſuming to be ſo bold as to think by your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments you have outſtript and gone beyond the word of God, as well for worth of matter, as excellency of ſtile, this were an abominable arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, and yet this is a crime too frequently entertain'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, to eſteem <hi>Calamy</hi> and <hi>Baxters</hi> prating before Gods word, alas they conceive that theſe men have outdone Chriſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58677:37"/> and his Apoſtles for preaching to the purpoſe, the common conſequence confirms this, for many had rather go five miles to hear one of theſe fellows talk frightful whimſies from their own brains, than to go one quarter of a mile to hear our Saviour Chriſts Sermon which he preacht on the Mount;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matthew</hi> 5.1</note> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37.</note> 
                  <hi>Peters</hi> converting Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the Jews, with other of Chriſt's and his Apoſtles works. The holy Teſtament which being read unto us with a pure heart, and we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of it with the ſame, undoubtedly it is the onely preaching of all preaching that doth moſt good, for what can be ſafer to be preach't than Gods pure Word which is able to make us wiſe unto Salvation? and though expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have crept into eſteem
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58677:37"/> amongſt ſome, yet I think that Chriſt and his Apoſtles Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons left for our inſtructions, are to be approved on before all other works of thoſe that love God. And next to the holy Bible, the Service of the Church pleads for prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence before any thing that ſhall appear for Service before God; for know that Prayer and Praiſes are the eſſentiall Worſhip of God, it is the Coyne of Heaven, it anſwereth all things, it pleaſeth God and pleaſeth Man, we have no other way to come unto God but by Prayer (through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt) Prayer brings us into his preſence, and ſhews us the light of his countenance; if God be angry with us, Prayer pacifies him and makes all well again; if we are in ſorrow, Prayer comforts
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58677:38"/> us: ſee this in <hi>Hannah,</hi> a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of a ſorrowful Spirit, Prayer maks her look Chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; If we are in proſperity, it ſtill refreſheth us more and more, like <hi>Moſes</hi> in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God on the Mount, our faces ſhine by it, our hearts are more clearly reviv'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I but ſay ſome, this Common Prayer is ſo mean a thing, that even a Childe may read it that can but read almoſt any thing, it is ſo inferiour that we cannot eſteem it with that worth as our Paſtors would have us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſounds ſomething like that ſin of <hi>Corah</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, to think meanly of the Service of the Church, that any man is able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Miniſterial offices as the Prieſt particularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated for the work, but
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58677:38"/> the puniſhment of <hi>Korah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> to thoſe that have read it; ſhould be a terrour and a ſufficient war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſtave them off from ſuch a curſed opinion. I ask the Queſtion, do you think that a Butcher or a Slaughter-Man brought up to that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, could not ſtrike down an Ox with more ſlight and agility than a Prieſt, or Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite? Why yes, no doubt but he could, common reaſon anſwers this; but this was not ſuffered in the Temple to be done, none but thoſe that have an expreſs warrant muſt officiate in Gods Houſe; 'tis true you may read the Prayers of the Church to the people, but by reaſon you are not conſecrated to that particular imployment, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſuffered by any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58677:39"/> allowance: <hi>Strange fire it is an abomination unto God:</hi> The Jews Liturgy it was as plain and eaſie to be read, as our Service, do you think that the Laitie could not have read the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> the Propheſies, the Pſalms of <hi>David?</hi> why yes, no Queſtion but thoſe men might have read theſe words, but not to any effect, but <hi>Aaron</hi> and his lawful Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors appointed and ſet apart for the work by God; for when the people are to be bleſt; 'tis <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons that muſt give them the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in Gods name, 'tis Gods Commandment, <hi>Joel</hi> the 2. and the 17. <hi>Let the Prieſts the Miniſters of the Lord weep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Porch and the Altar, and let them ſay, Spare thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58677:39"/> Oh Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Malachi.</hi> 2.7.</note> By the Prieſts lips muſt the people learn knowledge: <hi>He that heareth them, heareth me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt? <hi>And he that deſpiſeth them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth me.</hi> See here then the true dignity of a Miniſter, his Calling and Vocation is both ſacred and eminent. Now as Mr. <hi>Sandcroft</hi> obſerves there are a ſort of men but of ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Sandcroft</hi> in a Sermon at the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</note> that would pretend to be wiſer than their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, the whole world, yea even Chriſt himſelf, which undertakes to thwart the ancient Decrees and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of God, as to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of his Service and way of Worſhip, a ſort of men that know God and Religion no otherwiſe but by meer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that are Chriſtians from the ſhoulder and upwards, that whatever their brain
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58677:40"/> conceives, their tongue talks it for infallible Revelations; but in the Words of the Lita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi rend="blackletterType">From all ſuch good Lord deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They that deny the decent Order and Worſhip of Gods Church, deny all that's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and good, ſuch think any thing will paſs with God and ſerve his turn, his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Dunces, and his Service Nonſence, neither to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led nor appointed, but to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen upon the office and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance by chance, and ſo by gueſs accordingly officiate, and perform; but our God is a God of Order, and muſt be worſhipped in Order, not in confuſion; his Prieſts muſt be conſecrated, and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice premeditated, or elſe it ſerves not his turn, let us ſquare but one propoſal by
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58677:40"/> common reaſon in reference to this diſcourſe: had we any buſineſs with an earthly King of ſome weight and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein if we ſhould miſcarry in the delivery of our meſſage, we ſhould not onely loſe our ſuit, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the Kings diſpleaſure; how careful would we be to get words fit for our buſineſs, how would we forethink of them, be ſtill premeditating, writing, correcting, and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them all exact, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing might be miſlik't. Do you think our buſineſs with the King of Heaven ought not to be as carefully ſtated, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought, and conſidered on, knowing that all vain babling is abominable to him, and that we can never think to be too exact in thoſe words that muſt come before God in the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58677:41"/> behalf of our ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, leſt like <hi>Zebedy</hi> we be repulſed by our asking we know not what? 'Tis ill je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting with edg'd tools, it is a ſtrange preſumptuous ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to ſtep into Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with unthought of words and expreſſions,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccle.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Be not raſh with thy mouth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, nor let thy heart be haſty to utter a thing before God, for God is in Heaven, and thou art on Earth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:58677:41"/>
               <head>The White Robe.</head>
               <p>CAvills about maters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different in themſelves, are too much the quarrel of the times, and that which makes the animoſities the ſtranger, is this, that order and comely decency in Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice makes the pure Worſhip of God deſpicable, and that is objected too as one of the maine cauſes of it,<note place="margin">The Surplice.</note> which in it ſelfe is the embleme of vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous innocency, that that ſhould keep ſo many off from ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God in publick, as tis pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, is more then ordinary wonder; Now this is a great grief to many that know the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58677:42"/> way to worſhip God aright, to ſee ſo weake a prejudice live and do miſchief, and that upon no ſure ground that it can keep footing on: but let Antagoniſts vent their furious madneſs againſt that harmleſs Robe, and we that weare it, let them proclaim we are Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters becauſe we ſerve the Lord in it, in this we do appeal to God to judge between their cry and us; thus much wee'l condeſcend to ſatisfie the world, we never do account our ſelves the holier when this white garment is upon us, nor the unholier when it is off; we owne this Ceremony, as the body doth a fine garment, for ornament ſake, or as a late learned Writer ſpeaks, <hi>The Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the Church are as the body to the ſoul, the body being enlivened by the ſoul is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58677:42"/> very amiable, ſo Ceremonies with devotion is very comely.</hi> We uſe this Ceremony in the Church for ornament ſake, and its ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant reſemblance being a habit fitted for conſecrated Perſons to draw near unto God withal, for what more fit than white, that ſuites with the affection of joy wherein God delights to have his Saints praiſe him.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel</hi> 7.6. <hi>Malachi</hi> 3.1.</note> White it is the beauty that the Angels appeare before him in, how then can any, nay dare any deny the Church militant here on Earth, that ſhe may not ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie ſomething by action and rite which the triumphant doth really performe in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? This wearing of the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, or White-Robe at D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vine-Service, is an innocent, harmleſs and good imitating Ceremony, a thing more for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58677:43"/> order ſake, than for any abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity of Worſhip, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd into the Church, and made uſe of.</p>
               <p>We uſually have at the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Actions of Royalty and Juſtice, ornaments to beautifie and ſet them forth, and ſhall we only in actions of Religion account ornaments a ſtain and blemiſh? did we make wearing the Surplice at Divine-Service a ſcruple in point of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that if we left it off, and not uſe it it would incurre our damnation, it might then prove a ſtumbling-block to many but ſince it is received into the Church, worne and made uſe of as a thing indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, yet by reaſon of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of more neceſſity for comlineſs ſake, in Gods Houſe to be uſed, than not; I hope then without any offence it
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58677:43"/> being thus receiv'd into the Church, it may ſtill continue.</p>
               <p>I know ſome will object, <hi>We have no Scripture for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of it into our Church:</hi> 'tis true, we have no Scripture to warrant it in particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words, nor none to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allow it; 'tis of no great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence whether we have or no, for we uſe it not as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs command from Gods own mouth, but as an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Ceremony inſtituted by the Fathers of the Church for comelineſs ſake, and not ſo ſtrictly injoyned as it is ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined; and indeed I ſuppoſe it is not neceſſary that we ſhould have in Scripture ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs mention of theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular things we uſe in the Church, for this general is enough to know by Faith that things indifferent cannot
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58677:44"/> harm them that are of a pure heart; But though we have not any Scripture that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends it to us, or any Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that diſallows it to us, yet we may finde in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Hiſtories reaſonable ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction that the Miniſters of God ſince the Law, as well as when the Law was in force, have diverſities of garments to diſtinguiſh them from the Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as for their decency in their approach to God, Saint <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle at <hi>Epheſus</hi> wore a garment call'd <hi>Petalum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Petalius Seu. Lamina. St Chryſiſtom. Tertullian.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> the <hi>Martin Pontius</hi> the Deacon teſtifieth, that when he was within a while to ſuffer death, gave his <hi>Barum</hi> to the Executioner, his garment of <hi>Dalmatia</hi> unto the Deacons, and ſtood in his linnen gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. St <hi>Chryſiſtom, Euſebius, Tertullian,</hi> and other ancient
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58677:44"/> Writers makes mention of the white garments that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters wore in the Church of old, which doth plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that the Surplice hath been of ancient uſe in the Houſe of God, I and that too before the tyranny of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; though many ſay we fetch it from thence. But ſay the Surplice, or White Robe had been firſt invented by the Pope, I cannot be perſwaded if it had been ſo, that the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety of Popedom is ſuch,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Peter Mart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y</hi> in a letter to an Engliſh Biſhop</note> that whatever ſhe touches ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>files, and polutes, whereby good men may not be allow'd to put into holy uſes any thing that her fingers have toucht. Now this were a burthen too intolerable for the Church of God to bear; certainly without harm, this garment may be uſ'd in the Church, provided
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58677:45"/> it be worn and made uſe of with that reſpect we allow to it, and no other ways, for order and decency ſake; and not with any ſuperſtitious and idolatrous intent.</p>
               <p>It is eaſie to diſerne how willingly men of itching ears and perverſe mindes, are drawn and kept back from Gods pure worſhip, by the ſmalleſt of diſlikes; men ſtampt after the old Proverb, <hi>that ſtumble at a ſtraw, and leap over a block,</hi> that are ſo blinded by the Spirit of contradiction and averſneſs to that which is good, they think no way ſtraight, but their crooked ways, a ſort of refractory peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſpawn'd by the ſeed of blaſphemy and rebellion, that had rather ſee <hi>Hewſon</hi> in the Pulpit with a blew apron, than Reverend <hi>Laud</hi> in the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58677:45"/> Desk with a Surplice, an opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as prepoſterous as the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, men guided and ſteer'd as ſhips in a dark night before the uſe of the Compaſs was found out, by the rule of ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and dangerous uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, for how many of poor ignorant ſouls, that know little or nothing of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; that ſpeak evil of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters out of their reach and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, more from a common received prejudice from others opinion, than any true expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of their own, crying down moſt of thoſe things that they do by the hear-ſay of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; for I am perſwaded that there is not one in ten of theſe people that are ſo inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate againſt the Ceremonies of the Church, eſpecially this innocent Ceremony of the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, that have ever weighed
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58677:46"/> their diſlike againſt them, or it, in the ſcale of a moderate and diſcreet Reaſon, but at random abhor that which for ought they know, if they did but ſeriouſly examine the matters by charitable conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, they might like eſteem, and approve of thoſe things which now they hate and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor; for this is too evident amongſt many that they pin all their Religion, like or diſlike, upon the monſtrous productions of the giddy-headed multitudes, taking their faith on truſt from thoſe that have either invented it themſelves, or borrowed it of they do not know whom; not conſidering or conſulting with truth, whether it may be ſafe to adhere to or no, which indeed is the evident cauſe of thoſe miſerable Shipwracks
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58677:46"/> that Hereſie and Schiſm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volves men into daily.</p>
               <p>Indeed did this Ceremony of wearing the Surplice, by being received into the Church, thruſt or joſtle out any of the Worſhip, or leſſen the pure Service of God; or that it tended to any idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous uſe, that the people were to worſhip it, and to believe that without it no good could be done, then it were matter of ſufficient ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and denial, but being onely ordained, brought in, and received into Gods Houſe for matter of order and decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, I think it ſhould not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo odious as it doth to many: 'Twas the advice of <hi>Diogenes</hi> the Tub Philoſopher that when we heard a man ſpeak evil of another, before we gave credit to the words
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58677:47"/> he ſpake, we ſhould conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whether he that ſpake them had a prejudice or no, againſt the party he accuſed; intimating, that his word ought not to be credited that ſpeaks out of prejudice; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when we conſider the enemies of the Church, the little kindneſs they have to the Order thereof, of which God is the Founder; we know, and are confidently certain, that their invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate venemous ſpeeches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Decency, as well as the Abſolute Worſhip, is not out of any zealous conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, but from a helliſh and willful uncharitable gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying, being too common like the argument of ſome ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly women, that will be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate againſt truth and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe they will be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate;
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58677:47"/>
'twere happy for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that they did not make it their buſineſs as they do, to cavil about the Ceremonies of the Church, for while their whole time is taken up in ſpeaking againſt the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Chriſt, it is to be feared they loſe the Divinity of Chriſt: for commonly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and prejudice it fills the ſoul ſo full that it leaves lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle room for ought elſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides take any of the haters of Gods Worſhip and Order, they that ſpake moſt againſt it, thoſe forſooth will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that they are the moſt purely religious, not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>That he that bridleth not his tongue, his Religion is in vain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could wiſh that all animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities taken up upon ſuch
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58677:48"/> grounds as theſe may die, for it is a ſhame to Chriſtianity and true proteſtant Religion, that we that pretend to ſerve the Lord, of meekneſs, ſhould delight in nothing better than quarrels and diſturbances, and that too commonly about matters againſt which can be given no ſubſtantial reaſon; for ſhame leave off all childiſh and wilful perverſeneſs, and be inſtructed, come into Gods Houſe, and imbrace the truth, and with a charitable conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction view theſe Ceremonies underſtandingly, and you will finde them rather helps, than hinderances; rather Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments to beautifie the Church, than polutions to ſtein or blemiſh her; I am afraid there are ſome that when time was, ſpoke ſo much againſt the Church and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58677:48"/> her orderly decencies, when gain and rebellion prompt them on to what they did, that they are now aſhamed to read their leſſon backward, although in conſcience they know they are wrong, and ought ſo to do! Oh what a wickedneſs it is to live wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a known oppoſition to the truth, to deny thoſe things which they know are very truth indeed. Come, come, for ſhame give no more occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Satans predominancy, the Devil rejoyceth at the diſorderly confuſion that he ſees amongſt you, Satan laughs, and <hi>Babylon</hi> keeps holy-day, both hoping and deſiring the downfall of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly that which they deſire will come upon you, and us without a ſpeedy unity,
<pb facs="tcp:58677:49"/> according to that ſaying of Chriſt, <hi>A houſe and City that is divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand,</hi> this is infallible, and we muſt expect no other with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an uniform aſſent to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uth publiſhed in our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urgy.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:58677:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
